Curriculum Vitae

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge

September 4, 2017

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

Education

PhD — Computer Science May 2011 - Dec 2014 Purdue University, USA Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Master of Science — Computer Science Aug 2008 – May 2011 Purdue University, USA

Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering Aug 2004 – May 2008

> PSG College of Technology Anna University, India

Experience

Research Fellow, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851 Oct 2015 - present

Research Fellow, Darwin College, Cambridge Oct 2015 - present

Research Associate, University of Cambridge

Dec 2014 - present Advisor: Anil Madhavapeddy Cambridge, UK

Technical director of OCaml Labs leading the development of Multicore OCaml project. Applying programming languages and program verifcation to solve extreme-scale parallelism and distribution.

Research Assistant, Purdue University

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

Teaching Assistant, Purdue University

Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Graduate Programming Languages (CS565) West Lafayette, IN, USA Aug 2012 - Dec 2012 *Aug 2011 – Dec 2011*

Aug 2008 - Dec 2014

West Lafayette, IN, USA

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones

Feb 2012 - May 2012 Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D)

Advisor: Daniel Waddington

May 2010 – Aug 2010

San Jose, CA, USA

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language – a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Advisor: Sankar Chnab

Dec 2007 – Apr 2008 Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

Journal Publications

J3

C8

Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell

Jun 2016

J4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones Journal of Functional Programming (JFP)

Representation without Taxation: A Uniform, Low-Overhead, and High-Level Interface to Eventuelly Consistent Very Volume Stories

Mar 2016

ally Consistent Key-Value Stores

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan *IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin*, 39(1): 52 – 64

MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML

Nov 2014

J2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 – 674

Efficient Sessions Feb 2013

J1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 – 167
Invited paper

Conference Publications

Continuation Passing Style for Effect Handlers

Sep 2017

C9 Daniel Hillerstrm, Sam Lindley, Robert Atkey, KC Sivaramakrishnan
International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD)

DaLi: Database as a Library

May 2017

Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Thomas Gazagnaire, Anil Madhavapeddy, Suresh Jagannathan *The 2nd Summit on Advances in Programming Languages (SNAPL)*

Oral Presentation

Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores

Jun 2015

C7 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan
International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)

Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony

Jan 2014

C6 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL)

A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC

Nov 2012

C5 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan
Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC)
Best paper award

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

Jun 2012

C4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM)

	Composable Asynchronous Events	Jun 2011
C3	Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)	
C2	Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION)	June 2010
C1	Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)	Sep 2009
❖ Workshop Publications		
W13	A Memory Model for Multicore OCaml Stephen Dolan and KC Sivaramakrishnan OCaml Workshop	Sep 2017
W12	Effectively Tackling the Awkward Squad Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White OCaml Workshop	Sep 2017
W11	Mergeable Types Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Samodya Abeysiriwardane, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2017
W10	Concurrent System Programming with Effect Handlers Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White Trends in Functional Programming (TFP)	Jun 2017
W9	Eff directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan JSSST Workshop on Programming and Programming Languages	Mar 2017
W8	Lock-free programming for the masses KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tho Laurent OCaml Workshop	Sep 2016
W7	Compiling Links Effect Handlers to the OCaml Backend Daniel Hillestrm, Sam Lindley, KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Worshop	Sep 2016
W6	Eff Directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Workshop	Sep 2016
W5	Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy OCaml Workshop	Sep 2015
W4	Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2013
W3	Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)	Apr 2011

The Design Rationale for MultiMLton

Sep 2010

W2 Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek *ML Workshop*

Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads

Jan 2010

W1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP)

Technical Reports and Drafts

Featherweight Threads for Communication

Nov 2011

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan
Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018

Teaching/Advising

• Guest Lectures:

T1

- Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent 2015–16.
- Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas 2015–16.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:
 - Databases, Lent 2016–17.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2016–17.
 - Databases, Michaelmas 2016–17.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2016–17.
 - Algorithms, Lent 2015–16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2015–16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2015–16.
 - Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University
 - Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
 - Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:
 - Nicolas Assouad, ENS Paris, Hardware Support for Composable Lock-free Transactions, Mar 2017 Jun 2017.
 - Matt Harrison, University of Cambridge, Secure Decentralized Apps, Sep 2016 present.
 - Maxime Lesourd, ENS de Lyon, Verified CPS translation of handlers, Sep 2016 Mar 2017.
 - Philip Dexter, Binghampton University, Approximate computing for OCaml, May 2016 Aug 2016.
 - James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
 - Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js_of_ocaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
 - Theo Laurent, ENS, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
 - Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

Talks

A deep dive into Multicore OCaml Garbage Collector

System Research Group Seminar

Jul 2017

Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge

Multicore OCaml GC

Jun 2017

JaneStreet Group

New York, NYC

Composable lock-free programming for Multicore OCaml ABCD Meeting	<i>Nov 2016</i> University of Edinburgh
Practical Algebraic Effect Handlers in Multicore OCaml LFCS Seminar	<i>Nov 2016</i> University of Edinburgh
Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml PL Seminar	Nov 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Madras
Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml PL Seminar	Nov 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay
Effective parallelism with Reagents Facebook Faculty Summit	Sep 2016 London, UK
Multicore OCaml and Programming with Reagents LDN Functionals	Aug 2016 Jane Street UK, London
Effect handlers in Multicore OCaml Dagstuhl Seminar	Mar 2016 Dagstuhl, Germany
Arrows and Reagents Invited Lecture, Advanced Functional Programming	<i>Mar 2016</i> Cambridge, UK
Concurrent and Multicore OCaml: A deep dive Facebook Tech Talk	<i>Jan 2016</i> Menlo Park, CA
OCaml Platform: Update OCaml Consortium Meeting	Nov 2015 Paris, France
Multicore OCaml: Update OCaml Developer's Meeting	Nov 2015 Paris, France
Silence is Golden: Controlling Communication and Coordination in Distributed Darwin College Science Seminar	Databases Oct 2015 Cambridge, UK
Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects OCaml Workshop 2015	Sep 2015 Vancouver, Canada
Quelea: Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge	<i>Apr 2015</i> Cambridge, UK
Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems PhD Defense	Dec 2014 Purdue University
Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming Invited Lecture	Mar 2014 Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK
Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony PADL 2014	Jan 2014 San Diego, CA
Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud ML Workshop 2013	Sep 2013 Boston, MA
A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC MARC 2012	Nov 2012 RWTH Aachen
Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness ISMM 2012, Beijing Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge	Jun 2012 May 2012
Lightweight Concurrency in GHC Wrestling Wednesdays	May 2012 Microsoft Research, Cambridge
Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction COORDINATION 2012	Jun 2012 CWI Amsterdam

Service

- Organizer, Dagstuhl Seminar on "Algebraic Effect Handlers go Mainstream", Apr 2018.
- Program Committee member: PMLDC@ECOOP 2017, Off-the-beaten track (OBT) 2017, OCaml Workshop 2016, SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: ECOOP, TODS, JFP, POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.
- Organizer for Darwin College Science Seminar Series, Oct 2015 May 2017.

Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014, \$4,000.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.